so much like other symptoms that men
often associated with uh low tea or
assume that testosterone replacement is
going to fix sleep is a big one sleep is
usually the one that is responsible for
a lot of symptoms that we find
detrimental to our life or I should say
poor sleep or lack of sleep and often
times men feel well if I can go on
testosterone a lot of these symptoms
will go away the problem is that it's
not always and more often than not it is
not your low testosterone that is
ruining your sleep it may be the
lifestyle that you are leading as a
result of the low testosterone lack of
exercise uh lack of focus lack of
motivation which leads you to not line
up a schedule throughout your day lack
of caring about what's going on uh you
know letting your health go those are
things that are directly related to
having low levels of testosterone for at
periods of time the problem is that when
you get on tea and you expect within a
couple of weeks for all of that to go
away you have to understand that you now
have to do a lot of work to undo some of
the damage whether it be weight loss
whether it be starting an exercise
program whether it be changing your diet
whether it be eliminating various
environmental stressors on a daily basis
sleep is a very multifactorial aspect
and it is not a magic pill it's not like
you start testosterone and a week later
you sleep like you did 20 years ago uh
the the biggest tips I can give you in a
short period of time to improve the
quality of your sleep is first and
foremost stop using
Electronics in bed right before you go
to sleep people bring their phones their
laptops their iPads and their
televisions into their bedroom and they
usually fall asleep while using these
devices the light and the stimulant from
the device and the information you're
processing is going to uh prevent or
inhibit your pineal gland from releasing
melatonin
we need Darkness or a level of calm
levels of light not a big light in our
face we need to not be processing
politics and drama and World issues
right before we're ready to fall asleep
you need relaxation so eliminating those
uh stimulants from your bedroom right
before bed is going to be the best thing
you can do initially because that you
could do immediately starting tonight
changing your diet don't eat right
before bed if you're going to dinner at
8:00 p.m. coming home at 11:30 and
flopping over again you're going to have
a hard time sleeping the heartburn the
indigestion the burping the you know the
the the processing of the food through
your gastric system is not going to
allow you to have a peaceful night sleep
so I recommend at least 2 to 4 hours
prior to actually getting into bed don't
put anything in your mouth if you want
to sip some water that's fine but let
your body kind of relax uh from that
point forward uh don't go to sleep on a
full stomach if you you on the heavier
side and you know we see this in my
clinic all the time we we do intakes and
we tell guys they're a little heavy and
they say I'm not heavy I'm perfect for
you know I'm 58 210 no that that is
heavy um you need to you know I hate to
sound primitive you need to go back to
the BMI scale I don't care if you're
muscular or if you are you know fatter
from from adapost tissue your body has
to pump blood and your body also has
weight pressure on your chest if you
sleep on your back and you have a larger
chest you can be 5% body fat with abs
and and a solid bodybuilder you have
weight and pressure on your diaphragm
your body's going to struggle to breathe
in an autonomous State when you're
laying supine on your back so you need
to reduce the amount of mass if you
really want good sleep bodybuilders have
sleep apnea bodybuilders use cpaps um if
your neck is larger than you know I like
to use 17 18 in um the the the board's
question actually I saw one come up that
uh that said you know sleep apnea is
higher risk in patients with X neck size
it was 16 so if your neck is above 16
according to you know medical literature
you have a higher risk of sleep apnea
you may not wake up or remember that you
woke up but you're not going to be in
REM sleep so you're going to be
exhausted the next day these are just
little things you can do in terms of
supplements I love zma zinc magnesium
and aspartate it's a three in one really
helps to relax uh helps you to sleep
before bed I recommend three capsules
for men two for for women every night
before you go to bed bed if you need a
little meel melatonin whether it be in
tab form or sublingual nothing wrong
with that um there's a lot of things you
could do to improve your sleep thinking
that taking testosterone will do that
for you is just a Floyd thinking process
and uh you know in the long term
testosterone is going to give you the
ability and motivation to perhaps make
the changes such as exercise weight loss
Etc but in and of itself it's not going
to improve your sleep a whole lot
[Music]